[Music]
thank you
hello good evening good day everybody
and welcome to the latest episode of the
ask Abhijit show I hope you're all doing
very well
so as always before we get into the
questions let's see who all are there
what is there on the live stream on the
live chat I can see uh Giuseppe Nishant
drove liger exasperated Fargo shivagami
Devi Martian Illuminati Creek unique
tutorials
Melvin Paul Greystone
Taurus k8991 gaming
priyanshi Akshay the rock star
strangely proton sriram abhinav Surya
Deepak manohar Arun Nishant
uh
super Mania VNT doctor Amit Aditya
Amisha
foreign
red chili
Ravi rajinping
PK
vikrant son darang rakshita pramod
Indian Mastiff and lots and lots and
lots of other people I can see chiching
Hello uh Deepak manmat uh Illuminati and
lots of other people so hey I'm gonna
stop here now because it otherwise I can
do this all day and all night uh so yes
uh so with that said with oh I'm I
cannot greet everybody obviously I can
see a million more greetings I I I'm so
glad to have you all thank you so much
for being on the live stream right now
let's get into the questions what
questions do we have as always we have
very interesting questions so what do we
have Where Do We Begin let's begin with
this
so here is demonetization and I had this
video a couple of I mean a few weeks ago
I had answered the question about
demonetization or something like that
and I said that uh
demonetization erect Pakistan's economy
so uh lots of people disagree with this
and uh so let's let's take a look at
what people are saying suddenly
pakistanis forgot to print money that's
not what stopping them this is only
theory in logic why haven't they be been
able to print new currency notes not
convincing
uh
what's stopping Pakistan from printing
new Indian currency notes after 2016.
due to GPS enabled currency note feature
hahaha I think it's observed Pakistan
still has a currency a printing press a
new currency is very easy to print now
you can print it with a normal printer
yes A4 printer go to the shop
the other here's the currency note
rishikesh says Pakistan had factories to
print the Indian currency and blah blah
blah if they are so good then they would
have continued it's just it's all
coincidence it's all far-fetched
imagination so um this is just a sample
of the comments that I have got about
people who say that Pakistan would have
continued printing the currency after
they got the new currency so I am
completely wrong and I'm it's not
convincing convincing and so and so
forth that's what people are saying so
foreign
okay let's let's get rid of the
questions on the screen yes Ah that's
more real estate now yes so
so
people a lot of people seem to be under
the impression that if you have a
printer which prints money then when
India comes up with a new format of the
currency you know then Pakistan just has
to get the currency notes put it in the
printer do a Xerox copy
thus copy then million copied that's
what people seem to believe
you know
some time ago I had said this on I don't
know which which episode I had said this
that I am very glad to say that Indians
are less naive nowadays well clearly I'm
gonna have to eat my words here because
Indians are still incredibly naive I'm
not saying stupid there's a difference
between being naive and being stupid
Indians are not stupid Indians are very
intelligent but Indians are incredibly
naive right now if you look at these
questions it is naivete and I can see
people who apparently seem to be very
you know quite senior and quite educated
who are saying such things
you think it's so easy to pre to to
print any then why can't Pakistan print
the US dollar
or the or the or the euro
why
if they still have the currency the the
printing press or whatever it is these
guys are talking about
then if it's so easy to print any
currency even if you change the currency
features and everything then why can't
they print billions of US Dollars
billions of euros
millions of whatever else
why
think logically use a brain you the gods
have given you a brain use that right
India changed the currency seed
India changed the paper on which the
currency is printed first of all and
it's not paper it's cotton fiber it may
look like paper it may feel like paper
but it's cotton fiber it's 100 cotton
fiber in India changed all the security
features on the currency notes it's not
child's play to replicate all that
what Pakistan well I'm not gonna go into
the details but what Pakistan seems to
have had
is an authentic printing machine of the
Indian currency India was getting its
currency printed elsewhere outside of
India
and you need this specific ink and you
need all those features
and you need to be able to do that
so let's say you have a printing machine
and the ink and all the ingredients that
went into printing the 2016 but the
currency that existed before 2016. after
India changes everything that printing
machine is going to be worthless
okay that entire process is going to be
worthless
so I just don't and I mean
I think it's this is the fault of the
education system that people don't
understand these very basic things and
you will say that the education system
doesn't teach us about how currencies
are printed and all that well I would
say why doesn't it teach that I think
everybody should know these things
your teachers and your textbooks in your
in the education system doesn't teach
you any of these things these are
extremely important things we have to
understand how these things work
how do security features work in
currencies earlier we used to have a
thread in a watermark and whatnot now
the features are totally changed
and they are very hard to replicate
unless you have the actual original
printing machine and the same uh
the kind of cotton that India is using
now for the currency notes and all those
things it's not Child's Play It's not
like you go to your Xerox and you put
the currency inside and said thus copy
then that's what people seem to be
believing I mean look at these comments
look at these comments this is just a
small sample of the 50 or 60 comments
100 comments I get every day
about this it's so incredible to see the
the naivete that people are laboring
under
so uh clearly I was wrong when I said
that Indians are less naive nowadays no
I was wrong I'm gonna have to eat my
birds right here
so uh I would I would like to request
everybody please
don't and
people are unwilling to think if someone
says something why don't you first
investigate whether it may be right or
wrong instead of just giving you your
knee-jerk reactions now you're wrong no
you're this no you're that hahaha
think about things properly everybody
has a brain everybody has an
intelligence use that look it up all the
information is available online how are
currencies printed what are the security
security features that India has
introduced after 2016
do you think it's so easy to print
currencies then why don't you go to your
local Xerox shop and get your currencies
printed
you can do it but it won't work nobody
will accept those notes because
everybody will be able to say that
Clearly say immediately that those are
fake so please understand how these
things work it's not child's play the
Indian government is not stupid yes so
yeah that's that's what I have to say
please disabuse yourself of these
simplistic Notions of how the world
works the world is much more complicated
than what you think it is
it I just I can't believe the kind of
comments I get in these things good God
ah
anyway let's move on to something uh
else
all right Umbrella Corporation
the reason why India can't leverage from
this 470 Jets deal is which is 100
whatever billion dollars worth is
because there's no other option in the
market or the other than Airbus in
Boeing if India tries to pressurize and
try to leverage leverage this they will
simply say don't buy the Jets and
there's no other company who many that
manufactures passenger Jets Airbus and
Boeing act work as a cartel they have
complete Monopoly on aircraft
manufacturing they will never allow
other companies and other countries to
enter into the market previously
Bombardier Canadian company is to make
small passenger aircraft but Boeing uses
Lobby and destroyed Bombardier
restaurant Market the same thing Boeing
did with Embraer Brazilian passenger jet
manufacturer it still exists embryos
still exists and they still have good
planes both of these companies have
absolute Monopoly yes uh there's more to
this
uh don't you think India needs to
collaborate with other nations to
manufacture passenger aircraft to break
the Monopoly the cartel of these two
Western companies imagine how much
employment they could generate in India
if we have the technology and could
manufacture those 470 aircraft in India
we are paying a hundred billion dollars
to the Western thugs I believe aircraft
manufacturing to be one of the most
prominent decisive factor that
differentiates a developed country from
a developing country
and all that yes so I totally agree with
what Umbrella Corporation is saying that
airboat and that's the deal right Airbus
and Boeing are are a monopoly it's a
duopoly essentially uh for uh Airbus is
French Boeing is American and these two
control most of the aircraft
manufacturing industry more than 90 I
would say the Russians have the Yakov
levs and and uh
uh Sukhoi 100 Jet and all that the
Russians have the ability to manufacture
their own aircraft they they have a
number of companies that manufacture
passenger aircraft and have the
capability and you know originally in
the 20th century in the 1900s uh
the Russian uh company aeroflot used to
uh it used only Russian manufactured
passenger Jets so you had Yakov levs you
had two polaves you had uh I forget the
names I I was a kid back then a little
kid but yes I found those Russians
Russian Jets very interesting they were
not the most aesthetic looking Jets they
were kind of ugly and clunky to look at
but they worked they did the job so you
know so they had Yakov lives they had
Tupa leaves I'm sure they had
or okay these days we also have the
Sukhoi 100 and all that so the Russians
have the ability to manufacture Jets but
uh
the the Americans and the French have
gone way ahead of them way ahead of them
uh Embraer you used to have McDonald
Douglas which was a very interesting
very good company they used to have the
DC tens and all those planes back in the
1980s 1990s I'm sure those are no longer
I mean I don't remember last time I saw
one of those Jets you know so they've
been all phased out I'm sure I think one
of these companies merged with Boeing
and so on uh so yes now you have a Duo
pulley Embraer does exist they do make
good aircraft they they don't uh
typically serve the uh commercial Market
uh they they do have uh
those corporate Jets and and small
passenger aircraft and they have large
heavy lift planes as well that could
serve as military transport aircraft and
all those things so embryer is a good
company they have they have been around
for the for the longest time uh I'm sure
since since the middle of the 20th
century uh
so yes so the deal is that
essentially if you want to buy aircraft
passenger aircraft you have to go to
either Boeing or Airbus uh the Russians
don't seem to be quite in a position to
supply hundreds of jets neither is
Embraer in an instant position so that's
the deal that's the duo poly that these
two companies have and they essentially
have elbowed everybody out of the market
obviously they manufacture really good
plays except for certain aircraft which
have been problematic like the uh like
there were these two Boeing crashes
recently
yeah
one in Indonesia one in somewhere in
Africa
but yeah
so they have this Monopoly and that's
the reason why even though India has
placed in order for
470 aircraft we still cannot you know
extract any technology out of them they
will simply say we are not willing to
give you technology we'll give the
aircraft and if you insist then you can
go look at look elsewhere and there's
nowhere else to look that's the reason
why this the people who are claiming
that India should extract geopolitical
advantage or technology transform from
all this they seem to be badly mistaken
and I see some some very senior people
saying that India is is the Indian
government is being stupid and all that
I mean come on
yeah so so that's that's the deal now
the other question is about uh
should India collaborate with other
donations well well you know one
possibility is India should go ahead and
buy the Embraer company
the Indian government or a private firm
should go and buy embryer whatever it
costs buy it but I'm sure it's not as as
easy as it sounds I'm sure there are
obstacles to doing that I'm sure the
Americans won't allow this to happen uh
and so on uh India could possibly like
yesterday I was speaking about this on
the Indian interest podcast that the
Russians have offered uh joint
production of the Sukhoi 100 uh uh
aircraft which is a Regional Jet with a
with a with a range of about 5000 or so
kilometers roughly give or take and a
capacity of about 100 passengers so the
Russians are are saying that they are
willing to co-produce this with India
and manufacture this jet in India I
think that's an interesting uh offer
that they've made and we should
certainly look into that
uh that would certainly uh
well uh you know bring a lot of
employment and generate a lot of
employment in India and obviously we
could
pay for the technology so we could start
manufacturing those jets in India and
then once you have one piece of
technology one jet that you manufacture
you can take it forward you can you know
use that as the base model for creating
more more aircraft like we have the
pages LC they just mark one which is the
original initial model but that's not
the final model we're going to you use
the the learnings uh that went into
manufacturing into designing and
Manufacturing this aircraft into making
better aircraft so that we have a mark
one a then the Mark II and then we are
going to have the twin engine deck based
fighter and the amca which are all be
gonna be based to some extent in some
way or the other on the original Pages
design so once you have an aircraft that
works then you can start creating a
family of aircraft based on their
original design by tweaking and
modifying the design and that's how it
goes that's typically you know how
aircraft designs evolve
so uh we have opportunities the Russians
well the Russians are kind of in a
corner right now uh because the Ukraine
conflict and they would be more willing
than otherwise to cooperate with with
India when it comes to Joint
manufacturing of and Joint development
of various aircraft and all those things
so I think it's a great opportunity for
India and India should certainly go
ahead with this if you know if India had
the industry to manufacture large
passenger Jets then it would generate
millions of job in jobs in India Imagine
India places in order within India you
know imagine Air India places in order
within two in with an Indian company to
manufacture 470 or 500 aircraft that's
gonna create an explosion of jobs you
know
it's going to generate millions of jobs
in India so I think it's high time India
takes these things seriously India's you
know it's kind of disappointing that
India doesn't
things move very slowly in India
especially when it comes to cutting-edge
Science and Technology uh so yeah I
think I think the government needs to
take this up very seriously uh so yes I
agree with all the things that Umbrella
Corporation has said over here
right next
okay ananta Krishna says what are your
views on unidentified objects popping up
over the US and Canada and the near says
what do you think about the Ohio
Chemical leak that blasted a train and
why is no one asking questions to the
USA is it anything else than what they
are saying interesting question so let's
put some stuff on the screen yes uh the
week when I was not here when when I did
not do the live stream this thing
happened the Ohio uh chemical explosion
which is a massive incredibly massive
exposure let's put that on the screen
some of those things uh where are we
right so take a look at these tweets
from some people this is uh Alex stain
uh a journalist I think it's a
journalist
a host of some TV thing okay a massive
explosion and poisoning of American
citizens should be a much bigger story
why isn't the media taking more talking
more about Ohio uh yeah so it's it's a
major thing it's it's a very major
disaster it was visible almost from
space
the mushroom cloud and the and the
chemicals that went into the atmosphere
uh very toxic
carcinogenic chemicals and and there are
reports of
animals and birds and chickens and fish
dying all over the region but it's being
hushed up and it's very surprising such
a big disaster happens on the president
of the country doesn't even bother to go
there so it's it's very surprising a
controlled release burn is kind of is a
weird kind of corporate double speak
this is this will hurt millions of
people in Ohio and Pasadena for years to
come and so on yeah so vinyl chloride is
is an extremely toxic and carcinogenic
chemical and it was not the only one
there were many more toxic chemicals
uh and yeah this is a whole thread by
this gentleman Eric feigel ding
uh about this it's it's it's being
compared to Chernobyl and apparently it
was totally entirely preventable uh so
yeah it's it's a it's a very strange
thing that nobody in the US is taking
this seriously seriously the media was
quiet for the longest time but social
media brought this up and then the media
had to speak about it to some extent uh
yeah mass casualty incident being
reported massive explosion at a metal
manufacturing plant in Bedford Ohio so
this is a different thing but even this
is something that's happened and once
again it's kind of being hushed up when
you have environmental scientists that
were heading to East Palestine Ohio
where where this thing happened so there
was a plane load of scientists who were
going their environmental scientists and
the plane crashes apparently very
strange very mysterious
uh
coincidence there are no coincidences so
yeah you know it sounds like all
conspiracy theories but you know there
are no coincidence coincidences uh why
while you're looking at UFOs and
balloons
uh yeah nordstream is fine so the 50 car
trade derailment in East Palestine Ohio
which was controlled burned fish and
wildlife are turning up dead all over
the place the Fallout is at least 200
kilometers wide this was February 14.
today is February 26th it must be much
much more and then they are talking
about balloons and UFOs look at the
shiny balloon ignore what's happening in
Ohio that's essentially uh what the U.S
media is trying to do
uh more this is in Tucson Arizona
more hazardous chemicals leaking all
over the place something weird is
happening in the U.S I mean obviously
it's a large very large Nation
geographically much larger than India
and I think there are more than a
thousand Trail derailments every year in
the US but something is weird
uh look at this toxic chemicals being
spilled all over the place and all that
and there's this interesting tweet uh by
Jessica Abraham
so where is East Palestine the the plant
uh the trail the Train derailed and
exploded
this is all about February 23 so all
these things that that are happening
seem to be in a very specific location
uh in the Great Lakes region uh Ohio the
balloon was shot the Chinese balloon was
shot down uh over Lake Huron no it was
not shot down over Lake here on the
discovered it over Lake Huron or
something then there are there are two
train derailments explosion of a plant a
third train details a 7.5 acre fire so
you you know these are all apparently
coincidences uh well it's hard to
believe these things are coincidences so
these unidentified objects these
so-called UFOs that are popping up all
over the years in Canada these are the
it looks like these are being used to
distract the the public the citizens of
these nations from what's from other
things that may be happening so yeah
yeah you've had a train that derailed in
this enormous explosion happened and
huge release of vinyl chloride and other
toxic chemical chemicals into that
muscle but forget that look at the UFOs
yeah the UFOs all over the place so the
the US government for the longest time
treated people who talked about UFOs as
lunatics
they will be locked up in mental
institutions and all that you know so
anyone who spoke about UFOs or or
expressed a belief a non-septical belief
in UFOs
would be treated as they were mentally
deranged and you know they were they
were repercussions
severe repercussions to expressing such
beliefs or ideas or thoughts
for much of the 20th century
but now the U.S government the U.S
military itself is releasing videos and
images and all those things of these
things there's a sudden change in
tactics and strategies you know
so uh
so it looks like it's a diversion
diversionary tactic they're trying to
divert Public's attention from other
things that may be more important and
may you know be
the people should know about it but so
that's what's happening so what do I
think about the Ohio Chemical leakage
it's a disaster it's an environmental
disaster it's it's uh but I'm not sure
if it can become compared with Chernobyl
but yes people are indeed comparing it
with Chernobyl
and the media tried its best the US
media tried its best to to kind of
you know not speak about this but social
media is a whole different piece and
it's all come out in the public so yeah
that's the deal that's what's happening
and
I'm not sure what's the objective of all
these things but yes these are things
that are happening and they are
perplexing
samarth says with the West including
France being rigid and hegemonic at the
G20 are they okay uh how will India be
able to mediate and solve the Russia
Ukraine conflict do you think it would
have been easier to mediate if we were
at the money and didn't have any dispute
modern dispute with China
how will India be able to mediate and
solve the Russia Ukraine conflict the
question is why should India mediate and
solve the Russia Ukraine conflict is it
our business no
why should India get involved in this
why should India mediate why should
India solve this problem whatever India
does whatever the government of India
does whatever efforts the government
exerts have to promote India's national
interest
that's all
why should we play the role of a
mediator and Problem Solver for the
world do are we paid for that do we get
any benefit from that why should India
solve this problem
think about how things have gone after
the Russian invasion of Ukraine has
India
has it been harmful for India or has
India benefited in some way from this
I would say India has benefited greatly
from
the the events that are a Fallout
of the Russian invasion of Ukraine
now India is getting enormous quantities
of very cheap Russian oil not only there
India is able to export uh processed
petroleum products to the West uh and so
India is India's it's a win-win
situation from India in two ways
and it's it's uh certainly uh boosted
India's geopolitical uh stature
uh it has
not worked out in favor of China the
Chinese were hoping for certain things
which had not happened towards a
significant extent because of India and
India's actions so I think the Ukraine
war has been good for India I and and
you know I may sound like an evil guy
for talking like this but that's how
geopolitics works that's simply how it
works so why should India go and put a
stop to what's happening
let it continue
the world is changing
the old hegemenis are slowly eroding
for the longest time for almost half a
millennium it's the English-speaking
people who have ruled the world it's the
Europeans who have ruled the world now
it's high time things change and things
are changing
so I don't think India is India needs to
or India wants to or India should
mediate and solve this problem
India should find creative ways of
benefiting
from what's Happening there are problems
all over the world these are not India's
problems
uh so so that's that's how I see this
it may sound
cynical and kind of evil and selfish but
yeah that's how it works in geopolitics
every time there's a problem it's an
opportunity for other nations or even
for for the nation that's involved so
that's how it is so I you know and I
don't know about the West being
G20 there is no hegemony or geopolitical
the G20 level G20 is about economic
cooperation and and diplomacy and and
things like that the G20 is not a very
significant organization when it comes
to geopolitics it doesn't change any
geopolitical outcomes or shape any
geopolitical outcomes it's more about
soft power and more about economic
cooperation and such things there is no
hegemony there right now India is the
president of the G20 and India is doing
very well India is expanding uh the
activities more than any other nation
has done so yeah
so I think India should not waste its
time India is not doing that India is
being very realistic in pragmatic India
is not wasting its time trying to
negotiate with these nations Russia and
Ukraine are trying to Media or trying to
solve the problem
India is benefiting from it as it should
why did France leave nato in
1966 can it happen again an interesting
question uh 1966
what was the situation like in 1966 uh
John F Kennedy was dead and Lyndon
Johnson Lyndon Johnson was the president
of the US at the time if my memory
serves me right 1966. uh at the
beginning of 1966 India's prime minister
mysteriously died in Tashkent Uzbekistan
then USSR and the president of France
was Charles de Gaulle at that time so
what happened
France did not leave nato in 1966 that's
not what happened what France did you
see NATO is is
essentially we know we have spoken about
this lots of times NATO is a U.S led
organization it's been created by the US
it's
it's uh the U.S satellite States in
Western Europe
that's what it is it's a military
Alliance and uh the U.S has treated
Western Europe as a buffer zone to keep
Russia the USSR away and now it's
expanding eastwards and that's what led
to the Ukraine war so in 1966 what
France did see what the demands of NATO
are quite stringent
the demands of NATO in any nation that
is a member of NATO to some extent or
the other and more rather than than less
has to accept a collective form of
control over its Armed Forces
which means your army your armed forces
and their assets are no longer really
yours they come under the command
structure of NATO
yeah that is a loss of sovereignty to a
significant extent
and if you are a nuclear power like the
UK and France then there is a demand and
there is an expectation that you will
integrate your nukes your nuclear
deterrent with that of NATO
so once again your nukes don't really
belong to you they belong to Nato and
you you will integrate your deterrent
with that of the other North Atlantic
powers
that's again loss of sovereignty now
when it comes to the UK the UK was
deeply beholden to the US it became to a
significant extent as uh an extension of
the U.S
after the second world war because it
was deeply indebted so they had to uh
exceed to many of these demands uh they
discontinued their their ballistic
missile and rocket program they had a
very good space program the UK they had
excellent rockets and it was all
dismantled
because of budget cuts and whatnot that
was the excuse that was made but you
know the Americans they don't want the
UK to have an independent Space Program
they wanted UK to be toothless
and again the UK's new nuclear deterrent
their nuclear warheads are placed on
American missiles
not on British missiles
it started with the Polaris program I
believe in the in the 20th century and
I'm not sure which missile they use
today but it's American missiles and I
doubt very much very strongly whether Mr
Rishi sunak actually has the nuclear
button at his disposal I don't think so
I think the UK's nuclear deterrent
doesn't really belong to the UK it
mostly belongs it actually belongs to
the US I don't think Rishi sunak has the
nuclear button at his disposal all right
or whoever is the prime minister of the
UK Margaret Thatcher would have had it
John Major would have had it but after
Mr Blair Mr Tony Blair it all went
haywire and didn't go Haywire
the the control passed to the US most
likely uh so this was the demand that
was made on the French the French were
not willing to integrate to to place
their nuclear warheads at America's
disposal essentially that's what it
means and they were not willing to
accept American control over their Armed
Forces when you say accept Collective
NATO control over your Armed Forces it
means you accept American control or
Iran forces so France did not withdraw
withdraw from NATO France withdrew from
the NATO military command structure
it still remained an active member of
NATO after
1966. so French officers military
personnel continued to serve at the NATO
headquarters in Brussels and uh they the
France did continue various activities
uh
military activities other and other
activities in coordination with other
NATO members uh for instance you have
the the Balkan conflict uh in the 1990s
and the early 2000s the French were
definitely part of that the French
military was part of that as under the
NATO uniform uh another NATO alliance so
France was definitely a part of NATO but
it refused to do certain things the
critical things such as control of nukes
and control of your Armed Forces those
the French declined to accept those
demands so French the French withdrew
from NATO's military command structure
and they rejoined it in 2009 they
rejoined in 2009 so they lost a little
more sovereignty in 2009 so that's the
deal about this NATO uh Saga France left
the NATO military command structure in
1966 and rejoined in
2009 a gap of more than 50 years was it
50 years roughly 50 years roughly half a
century all right
okay
the guy
says as you said in your previous videos
that ISRO should get more Finance yes
what are your thoughts on the Indian
government reducing the budget allocated
to ISRO compared to the previous year I
think it's terrible
I think it's extremely disappointing
um
you know
I don't know what's the reason for this
but your space program is something that
you invest in long term it's gonna pay
you back in the long term not today so
if you're cutting down the budget of
ISRO it's kind of short-sighted behavior
you will cut down the budget and
allocate the money somewhere else but
you know
ISRO I don't know what ISRO is up to
you need to have a long-term vision
and plan and you have to implement it
step by step by step look at how the
Chinese do things look at how look at
SpaceX for instance
20 years ago SpaceX didn't even exist
and when Elon Musk decided to start
SpaceX he first went to Russia
in the hope of purchasing a couple of
icbms intercontinental ballistic
ballistic science for a few maybe tens
of millions of dollars or something so
that he could take that re-enter you
know reverse engineer it and then start
building rockets for SpaceX the Russians
laughed him off
so then what he did Elon Musk is he
hired ex NASA rocket engineers and and
of other folks who had the background
and then they started create went ahead
creating a rocket the first uh SpaceX
rocket rocket from scratch and there
were at least two or three launch
failures which which is to be expected
when you're starting something new
a rocket is extremely complicated
something or the other can fail and then
the whole thing uh
fails but eventually on their last
possible try when they were running out
of money the rocket launched launch went
off and they were able to uh gain
Government funding and that's half
SpaceX took off and today they they are
on the verge of launching the most
powerful rocket Humanity has ever made
in in less than 20 years they've gone
this this far
what is ISRO doing
hardly anything
SpaceX has more than a hundred launches
easily per year rocket launches
they have several rocket launches every
week at least one a week
if you look at uh for it on a monthly
basis multiple times a month at least 10
times a month
so they are
launching so many Rockets they are doing
so much business what is ISRO doing
nothing
very little
I'm not I'm not passing any kind of
negative judgment on the quality of
India's scientists and Engineers I'm not
doing that
that's not what I'm doing there doesn't
seem to be any ambition in the
leadership
so when it comes to the leadership of
Israel and I'm not talking about the
leadership within ISRO I'm talking about
the external political leadership
because it's always entirely controlled
by the Indian government and whatever
whatever Israel does is explicitly
something that that has been told that
that it's been told to do
it's entirely controlled by the Indian
government ISRO
so the whoever is the chief officer
doesn't get to decide what Israel is
going to do next that's not how it works
so if ISRO is doing nothing I'm not
saying it's doing nothing but it's doing
very little I mean when was the last
time ISRO came up with the new rocket
yes recently he sort of came up with a
new rocket which is a tiny rocket for
launching little little satellites
instead of making building larger
Rockets more powerful Rockets we are
building tinier Pioneer Rockets I'm sure
there's a reason why it's doing that
that's to make money to it's to launch
small satellites the purpose of ISRO is
not to make money for India the purpose
of future ISRO is strategic
it's to make India a major space Power
if not the greatest space Power and
nothing is being done on that front
very disappointing
when was the last time Israel came up
with a new power more powerful rocket
the gslv has been under development for
more than a decade
they come up with various different
iterations and versions of the gsmp
slightly more powerful slightly less
likely that I would like to see a 10
times more powerful rocket come up we
have the ability to do that
it's not being done in the by the end of
the 21st century the two or three
nations that are leading the world in
space exploration are going to be the
two or three nations that control the
entire world in India showing no
ambition to catch up
the Chinese are not some geniuses
India can surpass China in in as much as
little as a decade if we provide the
funding
to Israel
but that's not happening there doesn't
seem to be any vision
now where is ISRO controlled from in the
Indian government I'm not quite sure I
don't know I'm sure we can look it up
but yeah let's not do it right now so it
is extremely disappointing there are
some random here and there some some you
know some programs there is this
shukriyan program to send a a probe to
to Venus there is the new chandrayaan
program it will happen this year or next
year or whenever it happens the third
one the first chandran was in 2009 it
went well the second one was in what
2019 a decade later
it should have been six months later or
a year later
very disappointing and yes there was an
issue
it did not succeed entirely the Lander
failed at the last possible moment so
why didn't we send a new one six months
later we still haven't sent in the entry
I don't know what's happening there is
no leadership
there is no I'm not saying there's no
leadership there is no ambition and
there is I mean there doesn't seem to be
any ambition to make India great space
Power India is going to be left behind
very badly if it continues like this the
Americans are returning to the Moon
the Chinese are extremely
focused on their Moon program they will
also soon send people to the Moon
SpaceX could send people to the Moon
very soon a private company where's
India
it's extremely disappointing so
so the default entire is entirely that
of the government of India
it's not the fault of the scientists and
engineers at ISRO they so one one option
is to is for you know people to is for
us having private companies that that
build Rockets we've had a company
recently that launched a small rocket
which was more like a single stage
missile but yeah why not good
so many would like to see more of that
but I'm sure there's a lot of red tape
in the uh
in the business sector and all that so
yeah you know it's very disappointing to
tell you the truth what's happening with
this role
why haven't we followed up on that
why not send a more powerful a
better
robot robotic spacecraft to Mars why
haven't we done that the Mongolian
eventually powered off because you know
there's only a certain amount of time
that the battery can last so it was
successful we did a good job we got back
four or five images back from Mars and
after that nothing I don't know why
so there's there's a lot
that can be improved and I to be very
honest I'm extremely disappointed with
the government's attitude when it comes
to Israel I'm sure we need to spend
money on other play another other things
but there's a lot of wasteful
expenditure also
there are so many programs that are all
you know that that can be cut cut down
to some extent and the money could be
allocated to Israel we really need to be
serious about space exploration
I know there are votes to be had in
elections to be won and all those things
which is also very important I'm not
saying it's not the case if you lose an
election everything goes to hell so yes
you have to win elections and all that
you need to get the popular vote most
people don't understand what what's the
big deal about space I understand but
you still need to fund the Space Program
because that's the future in 20 years 40
years you know if India is not caught up
with China
or the U.S we're going to be left behind
way too badly remember in the 1990s in
the 1980s and 1990s Pakistan and India
were neck to neck when it comes to the
economy today India has gone so far
ahead of Pakistan that the pakistanis
can't even compare themselves with India
anymore
so that's what could happen to Israel
vis-a-vis NASA and SpaceX and the
Chinese place program in the next 20
years if you if we continue with this
attitude
there needs to be a 100 Year vision of
where India needs to be when it comes to
space exploration in 100 years
and we need to start working towards
that it's not happening very
disappointing that's all I can say about
this
okay Linda says this is a this is from
Twitter why is the English language so
you know what yeah why can't I spell
toast as t-o-s-t or t o s t also gives
you toast but yeah we have to write it
as t-o-a-s-t there is so the English
language is so incredibly arbitrary the
grammar is incredibly arbitrary the uh
spellings of words are incredibly
arbitrary the pronunciations are
incredibly arbitrary why is it so I mean
why did can't you just write the letter
Q instead of q-u-e-u-e why just not Q
so it's extremely hard for a non-native
English speaker to learn the English
language that's why people make so many
spelling and grammatical mistakes and in
India if you make spelling and
grammatical mistakes in English you are
regarded as somebody of inferior
intelligence which is pathetic which is
wrong
so why is the English language
the way it is why is it so
well it's not a problem with the
language itself it's the problem lies
with the script
the script that is used to write the
English language which script do we use
to write the English language the a b c
d e f g h that script it's not the
English script
it's the Latin script
in the Latin script is not is not native
to England it's it's an it's an external
imposition on England
the Latin script
emerged in Italy
in Italy in the pre-roman times
and it was the script that was used by
the Romans
during the Roman times and then out of
Rome emerged
the Catholic Church
the Vatican which was an Empire it
controlled all of Europe
and what it did was spread Christianity
and you can read the book there are lots
of books about this one of the best
books is the darkening age by Catherine
Nixie in which uh you you get to see how
Europe's indigenous culture was
destroyed
by Christianity destroyed through Force
through a lot of force a lot of violence
a lot of bloodshed
if you go to Greece for instance
and you see uh the great monuments of
Greece and the carvings wonderful
carvings and statues they're all defaced
and mutilated and destroyed and broken
arms are gone noses are broken off
hands are gone
other limbs are gone hammered off very
similar to what you see in India when
you go to temples in Northern India
they're all destroyed
in all the murtis of gods and goddesses
are mutilated in some way or the other
nose is broken faces broken breasts gone
arms broken
you don't see any intact statue of any
god or goddess in any Temple or any
other place in Northern India it's very
I'm talking about ancient
statues and pimples
you hardly find a statue of the Buddha
in Northern India and I'm talking about
including Afghanistan Pakistan which the
head still on the shoulders
we know how this happened a very similar
thing happened in Europe
with the expansion of Christianity
so if you go to Greece if you go to the
Hellenic Hellenic regions
you will not see it's very it's very
rare to find a statue that is intact
most of them are you know they've been
dumped in in Lakes they've been buried
underground they've been broken they are
lying in in Ruins and of late they've
been trying to restore all of this but
that's what happened that's how
Christianity destroyed Europe's
indigenous culture there were the
northern Crusades which were extremely
bloody
so Christianity spread through the sword
it spread through Force it's it's a
chapter of history that they the
Europeans try to brush under the carpet
yes
um
so with the expansion of Christianity
who came the expansion of the Latin
script and everywhere see Europe had its
own scripts let me give you some
examples of of European Scripts
uh that emerged outside
of Rome the runic alphabets for instance
that were used to write the Germanic
languages
there is some speculation here about it
may have been based on an early version
of the Greek alphabet so the Greeks had
their own alphabet you had the runic
alphabet take a look at this the Elder
futark the young of uttarch
the Gothenburg ruins latinize futark and
and a lot more there were lots of
different forms of the runic alphabets
these were typically used to write the
Germanic languages English is a Germanic
language they were used to write the
Scandinavian Teutonic languages the
Scandinavian language the the Viking
less language and all those things
there are lots of runestones that you
find across Europe so all of these
European languages
if they did have a script of Their Own
It was typically a runic script and
there were other scripts as well you had
other scripts in the in the Asian region
in Greece and all that so you had lots
of indigenous scripts that had emerged
in Europe all of these were wiped out
all of these were destroyed and a single
script was imposed over almost the
entirety of Europe that was the Latin
script and this was not a native script
to most of the European languages except
for Latin
so then they had to adopt a foreign
script
to write their language for the longest
time uh it was the Latin script was for
the longest time was not used to like
write the native languages it was only
used to write uh you know Christian
theological stuff the Bible and things
like that
so the Bible and and all that was
typically only written in Latin for the
longest time and that's a whole
different story but eventually the Latin
script which was the only script left
was then eventually adapted to to write
the various European languages including
English so in French
so I'm familiar with French so in French
you have these accents
you have this idea and things like that
in German also they have various
diacritical marks that they've imposed
that they that are introduced on the
Latin script to make sense of it to make
it more uh to adapt it a little bit to
the to the German language so then you
had these things uh the Russians use
this Cyrillic script which is a native
script so the reason why the English
language is so arbitrary the spellings
and pronunciations is because they it
uses a script that is not native to the
language and not native with the region
it's a foreign script that has been
Force fitted on the culture and on the
language and that's why it's so hard to
use it imagine the English trying to use
the Chinese alphabet do you write
English one word right
imagine Indians
trying to use the Chinese alphabet
the Chinese script to write Hindi
or Telugu or Tulu or kannada or Assamese
will it work it simply won't work it may
work to some extent but it's not gonna
work fine it's not gonna work perfectly
so that that's what happened with
English
a foreign script was hegemonically
superimposed and force-fitted on the
English language and that's why it's so
weird and that's why it's so arbitrary
and the pronunciations and spellings and
everything is so weird that's why it's
so hard to learn the English language
right next question
oh man once I get this question at least
10 times a day comments at least 10
comments like this every single day
so I'm sure you are all familiar with
this video on on my channel the Chinese
Khan video why Chinese can't refuse to
invade India
and uh I get this this comment at least
10 times a day I'm just but it's been a
while since I took it so let's take it
this is by Muhammad Adil
and Muhammad Ali says it's better to put
evidence and reality in the light of
History it all looks like speculation we
all know that Delhi Sultan khilji and
what he did to the army of Genghis Khan
and his army
so I get this like I said I get it all
the time and there are lots of people
who say who who insist that I am totally
wrong
that uh Genghis Khan did not voluntarily
go back it was he was defeated by
Aladdin khilji and his army so Aladdin
khilji was the great savior of India he
saved India from Genghis Khan that's
what people keep on insisting on day
after day after day
okay let's let's so
why can't people try and find the
information from and verify their claims
their own claims
let's go to Google yeah let's let's
let's see for ourselves if there is any
truth to uh what Muhammad Adil is saying
okay let's let's first Google simply
Genghis Khan
we have to write it as Genghis Khan not
all right let's see
Khan was born in roughly around 1162 A.D
he died on August 25 1227.
what year
1227 now let's go back and search for
foreign
[Music]
died in 1227. when was this gentleman
born
Aladdin khilji the great savior of India
apparently he was born in 1296. do you
see that Aladdin khilji was born at
least two decades after the death of
Genghis Khan if there is the case then
how can he possibly how could he
possibly have defeated Genghis Khan
please explain to me
dear Geniuses I mean
I just don't understand why people are
like this
why can't you just double check cross
check what you are claiming what you're
believing
it's so easy to do it it's it's your
fingertips pick up the phone and Google
it but you won't do it
the same time that it must have taken
Muhammad Adil to write this comment in
the same time you could have checked the
evidence for himself but he will not do
it
this I just I'm not sure which country
is from I am assuming he's Indian
I I don't get it why Indians are like
this
we insist on believing certain things
and even though it's so easy to check
the information and data for yourself
you will not do it
I just don't get it this attitude we got
to change
we got to improve
whatever your beliefs are today you are
in a position to immediately on demand
check check whether you are right or not
whether your beliefs are correct or not
so why don't you do it
what prevents you from doing it do I
prevent you from doing it does the
government of India prevent you from
doing it
does Joe Biden prevent you from doing it
does George Soros prevent you from doing
nobody's preventing him from doing it
so please I would like to invite
everybody all the viewers I would like
to exhort you all please
utilize technology
please cross check whatever you your
beliefs are please double check whether
you are right or not
all right
Rama Lakshmi says can you talk about
operation Popeye and did it really
affect the environment in contrast what
would be the difference between it and
creating artificial rain operation
Popeye so this is this is something that
goes back to the Vietnam War 1960s 1970s
uh the Vietnam War well the roots of the
Vietnam War go back to the second world
war and before but it's something that
happened in the 1960s and 1970s
uh so
in the Vietnam War it was about the The
Americans
well they apparently did something
called a false flag operation the Gulf
of Tonkin incident and they used that to
precipitate the war triggered the war in
the objective was to defeat communism
and bring in democracy and human rights
[Laughter]
democracy
so North Vietnam South Vietnam so North
Vietnam was the the the
so it was about
fighting the Communists and the
Americans were worried that the Chinese
will expand their footprint in Southeast
Asia and take over Vietnam and that's
what it was so it was about American
National Security half the planet away
apparently so
what this operation Popeye was about was
it was about
it was about creating artificial
rainfall
it was a chemical weather modification
program
right a military cloud seeding project
now cloud seeding is a technology that
does work today it does work what you do
is you release uh chemicals into the
atmosphere which act as nucleation
points those molecules act as nucleation
points the seeds for creating raindrops
you typically use sodium iodide or
silver iodide mostly it's silver iodide
that's the chemical that's used
and it's it's possible to produce
rainfall almost on demand within a
certain time frame by doing this thing
you typically would send a plane
aircraft up into the atmosphere at a
certain height you release these
droplets the the this chemical and soon
you will have rainfall
so you typically use silver iodide or
sodium iodide uh so this operation
Operation popi was conducted during the
Vietnam war
and the Americans did not and what was
the objective of this
the objective of this artificial rain
program this chemical weather Warfare
program The Objective was to unleash
rainfall was to extend the rainy season
in Vietnam in order to have this
unseasonal excessive rainfall that will
uh soften the roads that will wash away
Bridges and create landslides and things
like that that will be disadvantages
to the uh Vietcong the enemies of the US
the Freedom Fighters that was the
objective of this program of operation
Popeye and the Americans did not do this
merely over Vietnam they did it over
Laos over Cambodia let's go to the map
yes map finally we have to see the map
where is the map where is the map
where is the map
here's the map
where is southeast Asia where's Vietnam
uh you can Orient yourself going
eastwards from India and then we zoom in
zoom in zoom in zoom in so this is indo
they call it Indochina
we used to call it suvarna bhumi this
entire region uh Myanmar Thailand and
eastwards so Vietnam is this long
geographical region this country over
here and then you have Cambodia
then you have Laos what's capitalism
then you have Thailand so the Americans
did not merely do this cloud seeding uh
activity over Vietnam itself they did it
over Laos over Cambodia and even over
Thailand
that's what we know they did in
operation Popeye but the results that
they were able to achieve have never
been disclosed so we don't know whether
it was successful or not on or if it was
successful to what extent it was
successful and whether they were able to
achieve their military objectives of uh
creating landslides and softening the
roads and washing Away River Crossings
and things like that we don't know
because as far as I know they've never
disclosed it you know I've actually
looked into this I have not been able to
find any evidence of of what the results
were
so that's what operation Pop I was uh
they did this during the Vietnam war 60s
and 70s when did it start when it did it
begin at the end we're not quite sure
uh but that's what it was but yeah this
technology of creating artificial rain
through cloud seeding using silver
iodide or sodium iodide does work it is
something that is indeed used by certain
Nations
for certain purposes for essentially
creating artificial rainfall
Hinduism is the only culture which
wholeheartedly accepts and respects
lgbtq plus people I have many lgbtq
friends who respect and love their Hindu
Roots but there are many lgbtq who are
completely left lean support radical
organizations which will ridicule the
Hindu culture what's the reason for this
it is the indoctrination created by
education the education system
and the media
typically it's it's this indoctrination
is is placed into people's heads uh it
starts in a software during the primary
school level it becomes a little more uh
it intensifies a little more during your
secondary school that up to the 10th and
12th standards and then when it when it
comes to college and university
education that's where the hardcore
indoctrination is done
everybody goes through this
and most Indians because of this see
first of all they don't teach Indian
culture at all you you're not taught
anything about your culture in the
Indian education system and then once
you go to a higher level you're taught
everything things that are totally
against your Indian culture all lies in
Fabrications
so that's what happens
so despite
Hinduism or Dharma or Indian culture the
Army culture being the only culture that
has never ever done anything against the
lgbtq people whatever that is despite
that Lots there are lots of gay LGBT
people who think Hinduism is the epitome
of evil and all that and despite being
of Indian origin of Hindu origin so it's
all because of the indoctrination and
the brainwashing done by the Indian
education system the media the
entertainment industry and so on your
professors your textbooks mainly your
professors at the uh at the college and
university level especially if you are
in the humanities good God you are
totally brainwashed it's I've I've known
people really intelligent people good
people you know good human beings
who went into the humanities and come
out totally brainwashed and they're
still nice people good people but they
genuinely believe Hinduism is evil and
Indian cultures believe is wrong it's
bad evil
intelligent people well-meaning people
good people who
feel this way who believe who believe
very strongly that Hinduism is evil and
not only that they believe the Indian
nation is evil there are people who will
support China's claim on Tibet and
Pakistan's claim on Kashmir but they
will not support India's claim on
anything despite being Indian
and they truly believe it is right so
that's what the education system does to
you
so that's the reason why this so despite
when find me anything in the Hindu
scriptures
there are millions of pages of Hindu
scriptures The Vedas the upanishads and
so much more the Smith
so much more right
find me anything
which says which which uh goes against
uh which which discriminates based on
sexuality you won't find anything
yeah and still these people are
anti-hindu so it's not their fault
please don't hate them for whatever they
believe
uh obviously it would be good if they
could disabuse themselves of these fake
Notions
but yeah that's that's what it is so it
is in the education system and our
wonderful professors and teachers are to
blame for this I am not saying all
professors are bad I'm not saying ulti
all teachers are bad some of them
themselves have been brain most of them
themselves have been brainwashed and
they also believe it and they think they
are right and they think they're doing a
good thing
so that's what it is it's a system that
is self-perpetuating and obviously the
certain very high levels there are
certain very
agenda driven individuals in the
academic system especially the
humanities
so yeah that's what it is that's that's
the reason why it is so that's the
reason why we see this phenomenon so
very often
Rinnegan says a U.S company will invest
500 million dollars in Manipur is there
an agenda behind such huge pumping
enough money into money for interesting
question do we have a news report which
uh corroborates this yes right come on
let's go there
let's put that on the screen
so this is from the Indian Express and
this news report is from February 18
that's a week ago roughly
uh U.S company to invest a 500 million
US dollars in money boards tourism
according to Chief Minister Mr Bean
Singh
uh citing the willingness of several
other foreign investors from Argentina
Peru and Bangladesh to invest in the
State uh the chief minister said Manipur
will witness development in all sectors
so recently there was the G20 meet there
was a G20 meeting the B20 a B20 meeting
in Manipur in in moirang
it was most likely in moirang close to
imphal near the loktak lake where this
uh event happened it happened on what
date 17th and 18th of February somewhere
around that time and all these foreign
delegates came to India and there were
people from the US and various other
nations
there you go
the B20 meeting yes
so these certain Nations have said that
they are willing to invest in manipur's
tourism sector and various other sectors
so there's a U.S company which wants to
invest apparently 500 million dollars so
uh is there any kind of agenda well
first of all when you invest money in in
a nation in a state it's a business move
your agenda is to make money I'm gonna
invest x amount of money and I will I'm
hoping to profit y amount of money
so first of all you invest money you uh
maybe you invest in the hotel sector or
or the adventure tourism sector or what
whatever sector which is going to which
is linked to tourism
you invest the money you create some
infrastructure or you whatever you do
and then over time after a certain
amount of time you hope that you will
make the money back and then you'll
start gaining making profits so the
first agenda is that you want to make
money
but obviously when the US is involved
one has to be careful because there can
always be other agendas
uh so as far as I see I I don't even
know which company it is I've not been
able to find the name of the company uh
in the news reports thus far so unless
we know what company it is and what
their background is and what what their
links are you can't really tell but
there's always the possibility that when
there is foreign investment in your
country especially in a sensitive area
like the Northeast like the Far East of
India which is a border region and where
which has seen problems in the past one
has to be really careful as to whom you
allow to invest in this place obviously
it's good half a billion dollars is a
lot of money and it's going to
significantly boost money money post
tourism sector economy if this is true
but the question is at what price are we
doing it so what uh kind of company is
it what kind of people run the company
are involved with the company what kind
of links does it have to other people
other companies and other people what
are the sources of funding who are the
the main people what are their
antecedents what's their background all
this due diligence will have to be done
by the government of India
it has to be done because it's always
possible that there is some agenda apart
from making money yeah
so for instance there are you will in
the Northeast you will find various
organizations that are linked to the
Christian Evangelical sector who say
that we are building hospitals in
schools but they have a different agenda
as well so one has to be careful about
this that's how the Northeast has been
brutally you know what's happened there
Krishna says we all know the situation
of Pakistan very soon they'll go out of
money well I'm not sure about that but
yeah it's it's in Dire Straits it's been
a Dire Straits for a while uh so in the
desperation for getting money will they
sell their nukes hmm
not the complete bomb but in parts we
know there are nations like Saudi Arabia
and Iran in the region that aspire to be
nuclear Powers if this happens how will
it impact India and how can and can this
be stopped from happening
so uh yeah Pakistan's economy is in Dire
Straits they they're on always on the
verge of defaulting they're always on
the verge of verge always on the verge
of bankruptcy but they keep keep on
being bailed out by their beneficiaries
in the past it used to be China nowadays
you have the US and obviously the
bailout will be done at the cost of
something or the other
so there's always a pound of Flesh to be
extracted when you bail somebody out
that's how it works in geopolitics
especially with Western Nations
and now I'm hearing this the the this
chatter on social media these days that
maybe Pakistan uh should
sell a few nukes maybe to Turkey maybe
to Saudi Arabia maybe to Iran
and make some money so
um
there's this guy who wears a red cap or
something who has been saying this that
Pakistan should openly no not do it
understandably do it openly this is our
technology we have developed developed
it apparently and now we have Pakistan
may have 150 nukes let's sell five nukes
or 10 nukes a few maybe to Turkey a few
maybe to Saudi Arabia a few maybe to
Iran and let's make money in this manner
well
first of all we have to understand that
the Pakistani nuclear program
uh was aided and abetted by the West in
vagina
so certain designs of centrifuges Etc
were were stolen stolen stolen like they
say by Abdul qadir Khan from
the Netherlands somewhere from wherever
it was he was allowed to take it okay
the West allowed the pakistanis to do
this
and then some help came from China maybe
um
uh
the Chinese transferred North Korean
technology to Pakistan or whatever so
Pakistan has been helped by the West
which means the U.S and by China in
creating its nuclear program and the
objective obviously is to counter
balance India is to keep India off
balance is to keep India a checkmated so
to say nuclear Checkmate so when the
West has such a large stake in this
why will they allow Pakistan to do this
even if let's say Pakistan wants to do
something which is apparently in
Pakistan's National interest will the
West allow this to happen Imran Khan is
prime minister wanted to make Pakistan
more independent of the West he wanted
Pakistan to have more more self-reliance
to be a self-respecting nation see what
happened to him
there's always the possibility of a coup
in Pakistan so the West does not want
Iran to acquire nuclear weapons the West
does not want any other Nation to
acquire nuclear weapons neither turkey
nor Saudi Arabia
so first of all if the if the U.S
doesn't want something to happen it's
very hard for Pakistan to do that
and even if they go ahead and do such a
thing I mean it would be a problem even
for Saudi Arabia to acquire a nuke
from or a bunch of nukes from from from
from Pakistan the Americans won't allow
this but Saudi Arabia is to a large
extent controlled by the U.S
uh turkey is a different story but once
again The Americans
see
what happens in Pakistan
is actually well known to the US there
are no secrets in Pakistan the Americans
have their intelligence assets deeply
embedded in the Pakistan military in the
Pakistan civilian sector in the Pakistan
nuclear sector in the Pakistan Pakistani
Italian sector bureaucracy government
everywhere
so it's not like the pakistanism can
quietly do something the Americans will
know everything and they won't allow
this to happen when it comes to India do
we want a new nuclear power in the
neighborhood do we want a nuclear Iran
Iran has Imperial Ambitions of its own
do we want a new nuclear power
apart from Pakistan
we don't want that
it doesn't benefit India it doesn't
benefit anybody to have more nuclear
powers in our neighborhood
so uh
so will the seller nukes I think they
may think of selling the nukes but I
don't think any of the Americans or
anybody else will allow them to do it
it's nice to talk about it and pretend
to be a great geopolitical expert but
it's it's extremely impractical if not
unfeasible completely
weibof says drdo Chief said that the
advanced medium combat aircraft the amca
will take its first flight in 2030 and
the induction will begin in 2033. don't
you think it's too late we should
consider Russia's offer of 75 s257 or
order a huge number of pages mark one a
to fulfill decreasing squadrons question
mark
yes the amca will most like most likely
the first prototype will first fly in
2030 and the induction will start in
2033 that's the timeline that we have
that's the timeline that's been given to
the government that's what's been
communicated to the public
do I think it's too late I don't think
it's too late when it comes to the
development of any aircraft it typically
takes a decade or two
look at the development timeline of the
F-35 the American F35 or the F-22 look
at the development time of the rafale
that we are now using all these are
extraordinarily complicated complex
machines
it's not like in the second world war we
had the Spitfires that you could knock
out you know 20 a week or whatever you
know it's not like that Mustangs P51
what is it p6151 Mustangs Spitfires
Schmitz Henkels
Rush
Japanese zeros those were low-tech
aircraft compared to what we have today
is fighter planes are extraordinarily
complicated many of these fighter planes
are aerodynamically unstable but you
make them unstable to give them more
maneuverability but then you have to
control the flight through computers and
you need a huge amount of computing
power and extremely sophisticated
software to do that because your plane
is aerodynamically unstable
so the more maneuverable you want your
fighter plane to be the more well you
have to introduce some kind of
aerodynamic instability in the fighter
plane which means you can't it can't fly
itself it has it it needs a computer to
fly it with the avionics rules and all
those things so
it and and the the amca is going to be a
fifth generation fighter plane with
significant stealth features and other
characteristics and India is essentially
developing all these Technologies on its
own because nobody is going to sell this
technology to India so it's gonna take
time
2030 I think it's a kind of an
optimistic time frame just seven eight
years from now but I hope it works out
in the time
uh India obviously has learned a lot of
lessons from the pages development
program the LCA Pages development
program uh the the mark one is coming
out the Mark II will come out in a few
years we also have the twin engine deck
based fighter that's going to come out
in a few years and the amca so I think
it's a realistic time frame if not a
slightly optimistic time frame uh I
don't think it's too late it typically
takes that much time to develop a
fighter plane so then what India should
do is
we need to find stop Gap solutions for
the next 10 or so years
15 years
because it's going to be by 2035 that
India will have a significant number of
these fighter planes indigenous fighter
planes inducted hopefully
so for the next 10 15 years we need to
find stop Gap Solutions one possibility
is that you buy more rafales the other
possibility is that you co-develop the
Sukhoi 57 uh no it's already called it's
already developed so maybe you could
manufacture that in India tell the
Russians that yeah we want to
manufacture at least 100 of these so
then they will move the manufacturing
facility to India it will generate jobs
and we will also hopefully gain gain
some technology transfer to the to the
through that or maybe we co-develop the
Sukhoi 75 with the Russians now we tried
to develop the uh the fifth generation
fighter aircraft with the Russians
co-develop it we gave them a bunch of a
certain amount of money
but they were not willing to transfer
the technology
so that money was sunk it was lost in
India withdrew from the from the program
that and that that program was based on
the Sukhoi 57 so we know what the
Russians can do they are not always
gonna play ball uh they will try their
best to not transfer the technology
obviously that's how it goes so you know
one has to be careful with these things
so one could co-develop the 75 so code
75 which has which is a certain kind of
fighter plane with the Russians maybe it
will fill in one of the gaps in our
requirements maybe we could buy some
super 57s I think that the Rafal is a
far better alternative it's kind of
expensive but yeah well good technology
costs money it's a very capable fighter
plane so one could go for the rafale one
could buy the F-16 the Americans want us
to buy f-16s or the f-15a uh hornet
or the Sukhoi order or the 57 5775 we
have a bunch of options or we could
order a huge number of pages mark one a
fighter planes uh all these
possibilities exist clearly we need a
stop Gap solution for the next 10 15
years uh maybe maybe a hundred fighter
planes of some kind
the best possible fighter plane we can
afford uh so that's what the government
to decide
uh so I don't think the amca development
timeline is very late I don't think it's
too late it takes time to develop a
really world-class fighter plane and the
AMC is going to be one of the best
fighter planes in the world that's the
objective so that's not gonna be
easy to do it's gonna take time
so the time frame is fine so we need to
find a stop cap solution in the
meanwhile the easiest thing to do is to
buy
maybe you know a total of approximately
100 rafales that's the easiest thing to
do because we already operate the rafale
and we don't want to have a big mix of
different kinds of fighter plane because
that becomes a logistical nightmare so
maybe the rafale makes sense
unless the Russians give us a good
technology transfer deal in which case
we could look into that as well so these
are the options that we have and the
government and the military should need
to get together which I'm sure they're
doing and they need to find the best way
forward and that too don't take too long
to decide typically these things take
decades to decide which is
incredibly slow and that's bad for
India's national security
Varun Joshi says
could you please
share light on the tartu sport and its
significance Israel bombed Damascus
Syria last week after the tragic
earthquake click 19 people why does
Israel keep attacking Syria during such
a humanitarian crisis okay let's talk
about the tartho sport one question at
the time well let's talk about tatus so
this port to understand we that we
obviously have to go to the map because
the map is our best friend
this sport Tartus or whatever the
pronunciation is is in Syria where is
Syria it's on the Eastern Mediterranean
Coast how do we locate it we go
westwards from India
we cross Iran and the Saudi and the
Arabian Peninsula and then we come to
the Mediterranean Coast the eastern
coast of the Mediterranean Sea and you
have Syria over here all right so Syria
is a largest Nation the large cities are
obviously Damascus Damascus in the South
you have homes somewhere here
homes in the west Aleppo in the North
and then you have a couple of ports on
the Mediterranean Coast one is Latakia
one is Tartus
so what's the significance of the tarto
sport let's zoom in
this is the only Russian operated port
in the Mediterranean Sea
and it's most likely one of the few uh
military bases that Russia has outside
of its uh
geopolitical region of influence so
let's go into this thing let's open the
satellite imagery
so this is a port that sometimes the
Russians would uh birth some warships
over here but it's typically used for
refueling their warships
so uh why is it important
so first of all it's the only one of the
only military bases the Russians have
outside of it there is a zone of
influence the Russians have this massive
black sea Fleet in the Black Sea region
where the Ukraine war is happening the
Crimean Peninsula belongs to Russia now
they are in control of it and when the
Russians want to send warships into the
Mediterranean Sea they have to do it
through the Turkish choke points The
Straits the Strait of Bosphorus that
passes through Istanbul
then you have to go through the Sea of
marmara and then you have to come
through the Strait of the Dardanelles
so once you are out of the spread of the
diagonals you have to navigate the
agency and then come into the
Mediterranean Sea
and obviously you will have to refuel
and Supply your ships somewhere so
that's what the part of Tartus is all
about it's a place where the Russian
warships can be refueled and refitted
resupplied all those things can be done
over here so that is the significance of
the tartu sport it's a Russian naval
base and I'm not sure we can see any
naval ships over here yes this seems to
be a naval ship possibly
uh yeah but that's what it is about
tartu Sport and it's not the only
military facility Russia has over here
so if we go north of Tartus we come to
Latakia where is not
exactly operated by Russia but there is
an interesting Russian presence near
Latakia it is over here
whatever it's called
and as you can see there's this air
strip over here it's an airport over
here
it's called the basal al-assad
international airport but it's actually
a Russian Air Force Base
right that's what it is it's
south of Latakia now let's Zoom a little
bit into it and see what what we can
discern from the satellite imagery so
clearly immediately we see this aircraft
over here these are very clearly Russian
aircraft
uh shall I zoom in further this is an
avax system Airborne control and warning
system and there are other places well
these are heavy lift uh aircraft of
Russian make very clearly yeah so we can
see the Russian presence over here let's
see what else we can see over here find
over here excuse me I can see some
helicopters
so these obviously are most likely also
Russian helicopters they look like
alligators
most likely Russian alligator
helicopters
this is a different make but yes these
are Russian helicopters what else do we
see what else do we see aha look at this
these what is what kind of aircraft is
this it's most likely
a MIG or a Sukhoi of some kind
so once again these are Russian fighter
planes these are all Russian military
assets
so that's the Russian presence in Syria
the Russian presence in Syria obviously
was required to save Syria from the
American attempt to change the regime of
the muscle of uh of Mr al-assad
and the the Russians were able to
successfully
save
the Syrian government
and that's why they have this military
presence in in Syria and the tartu sport
the Russian presence in the tartar sport
dates back to the USSR days to the 20th
century so it's not something that's
happened recently it's it's been there
for the longest time
all right
okay what's the next question
wbcs says do you think to protect Dharma
we should start eating beef and taking
testosterone injections should we not
try to make our men battle ready more
milk more physical culture and so on
what's the utility of weak iitians and
doctors we are losing ground because of
not lack of faith but lack of strength
and aggression
um you know
I would I would agree that everybody
needs to be physically fit and active
and strong that's why I keep saying
everybody needs to take care of their
health to lift weights eat good food eat
a healthy diet I'm not sure anybody
needs testosterone injections it's true
that the testosterone levels of men are
are
falling worldwide it's a global
phenomenon
but uh so so the question is how do you
increase your testosterone and be more
manly or whatever yeah what testosterone
does is it gives you the masculine
characteristics more muscle mass
compared to females uh the
characteristic phase of the shape which
is more Square compared to that of
females and more muscle mass more bone
density a higher strength the deep voice
that men have all those characteristics
and more aggression the higher the
testosterone the more aggressive you're
going to be so uh you don't need
testosterone injections to do that
these the easiest way to increase your
testosterone is to indulge in heavy
physical activity lifting weights and
the best weight lifting exercise for
increasing your testosterone is legs
that's squats you take a barbell you put
it on your shoulders and you go down and
you come up that's called a squat the
squat is is the best testosterone
boosting exercise it's it's a very
difficult exercise especially if you
have a heavy weight that's why leg day
is the hair is the hardest day right but
yeah so you don't need to take
testosterone injections for that
now when it comes to eating beef it's
the one thing that's Taboo in Hinduism
so why would you do that I understand
what you're what you're trying to say
Indians need to eat more protein and all
that so you don't need to eat beef for
acquiring protein you could eat chicken
you could eat fish you could you could
even acquire the gain the same amount of
protein from vegetarian sources like
pulses and all that so it's not required
it's not needed to eat beef to be more
masculine now think about it like this
some of the fiercest Warriors in human
history when the Japanese Samurai right
we know that
some of the best warriors of all time
the samurai do you know the samurai were
vegetarian
the samurai were vegetarian
and if you don't trust me
then let me offer you evidence
here we are
why eating meat was banned in Japan for
centuries
so you can look at this article
for centuries the Japanese people
considered eating beef especially taboo
now they're not Hindus right apparently
so why was eating beef a taboo in Japan
so that's a whole historical thing
it's what I keep saying all the time
Hinduism and Buddhism are the same thing
this contrary to what 99 of Indians
believe
um
so uh so eating meat was taboo
especially beef
it was Taboo in Japan uh what did the
samurai really eat in a day
so Samurai the history of the Samurai
predictably Samurai ate a lot of rice
and all that pickled herbs vegetables
four minutes paste miso all those things
vegetables leafy vegetables root crops
and so on and so on but where's the beef
yeah the beef is missing from the
samurai diet
they did not eat a lot of meat the only
meat they would eat if at all would be
fish or seafood
both practiced in ancient Japan
considered both of these religions
considered meat unclean and encouraged
followers to eat
vegetables or fish but not meat
so that's what that's a that's a deal
the samurai the vegetarianism was
something that the samurai had in common
with ninjas so even the ninjas were
vegetarians
right
so the great warriors some of the
greatest warriors in the world the
samurai were vegetarian Ninjas the
greatest assassins in the world were
vegetarians so you don't need
to protect Dharma to you don't need to
eat beef to protect Dharma and take
testosterone injections the great
Samurai is the great some of the
greatest warriors were vegetarians
nobody has accused them of being not
manly enough or not being martial enough
or not being strong enough right
even the the the Roman gladiators were
mainly vegetarians and those were
trained their only purpose was to fight
so this myth that people have many
people have I mean we need to re-examine
that it is not based in in fact and yeah
the easiest way to uh to to consume
sufficient protein is to eat meat I mean
you could also eat milk products yes you
could eat paneer or cheese but the
easiest simplest ways to eat meat so you
don't have to eat beef for that you
could eat chicken you could eat fish you
could eat uh other meat products
so I agree that uh it is good to be
physically active physically strong
that's what I keep recommending to men
as well as to women boys as well as well
as well as girls you need to be
physically active you need to be
physically strong even girls need to
have this go to the gym lift weights yes
um
that's what I ought to say but the other
thing is that what's the utility of weak
iits and doctors listen in a society you
need all kinds of people
you need you have division of labor in
any functioning Society you need
intellectuals you need doctors you need
Engineers you need scientists you need
artists you need merchants
you need Warriors
not not everybody does these things
everyone's different everybody needs to
find what they are the they have the
most aptitude for and go for that
and there are people who who obviously
have the aptitude for physical activity
and warfare and all that well those
people should
do whatever is right
to be physically strong and fit and
that's how it is yeah so I disagree that
there is no utility of weak IIT and
doctors I agree that in Indian Society
there is this uh kind of shift
uh away from physical culture if you
watch Indian Entertainment all the men
you see are kind of effeminate if you
watch Indian advertisements
especially those aimed at teenagers the
boys they show In Those ads are very not
not quite manly even though you have
physically stronger and more manly Boys
around but the the ads only show certain
kinds kinds of men or boys so yeah there
is this and and that's something that's
seeping into the consciousness of
youngsters
so it's it's cool to be you know
less manly these days that's that's
something that's seeping in from the
West we know how the social political
climate is in the U.S and in the west
right so I think uh every person
needs to take care of the health I think
every I think weight training will
benefit everybody
heavy weights not little weights yeah no
not those little pink dumbbells but real
iron weights you need to
test yourself
you need to try and go beyond the limits
not enjoy yourself obviously so I think
everybody needs to do that but I think
there's a great amount of utility when
it comes to iitns and doctors and
scientists and engineers and
intellectuals and writers and artists as
well as merchants and entrepreneurs and
warriors a good Society a healthy
Society needs all these people
laughs
luncheon buses are methes private Hindus
with their own version of the scriptures
called puyas puyas a tinga is Brahman
shidaba is Shiva Sanam he is Ganesh The
Vedic Age seems to be only 3500 years
old the kanglasha the beasts are
supposed to have only one horn it's the
same as the Chinese dragon lion okay the
first of all the Vedic Age is not three
and a half thousand years old that's
what romira thapar would like you to
believe that's what Irfan Habib would
like you to believe that's what your
education system is has been drilling
into your heads The Vedic system is way
older than that The Vedic Age
it is tied to the to The Disappearance
of the Saraswati River so I'll I'll not
go into the reason why the Vedic Age and
the rigveda is way older than what these
people claim it's it dates back to at
least
five six thousand years before today if
not much more at least we don't know
quite exactly how old it is but it's way
before that the rigveda is the oldest
known literature in in the entire
history of humanity so The Vedic Age is
not three and a half thousand years old
now the question about the myth is the
methods are the people of Manipur where
is Manipur I hope you all know and in
case you don't let me um
let me
um go to the map as always where's the
map where's the map
where's the map so where is Manipur
let's find moneyport Moneyball is in the
Far East of India which people
colloquially call the Northeast
south of nagaland north of nizoram West
of Myanmar
this is Manipur
it used to be a kingdom
it is now a state
and the geographical collection of
Manipur was larger than this in the past
uh India gave away the kabo valley of
Manipur to Burma under the great SRI
jawaharlal nehruji the great man himself
um
now
so the and the methane people are the
people of money but the Hindus the the
the the
Hindus or the Sanam people Sanam
following people of Manipur those people
are called the metis and uh
so if you look at the history of Manipur
it dates back
at least 2000 years if not three and a
half thousand years
uh there is the the Royal Chronicle of
Manipur which is the record of the kings
of Manipur in the dynasty of the royal
dynasty of Manipur one version is it
dates back to around 2000 years before
today and there's another version more
extended version that dates back to
three and a half thousand years before
today
now if you look at the Chinese history
it is about 3000 years old if you want
to be charitable to China it's three and
a half thousand years old I'm talking
about the actual civilizational history
of China if you look at the Stone Age
and all it goes back thousands of years
but we talk about the civilization
Institute of China so Chinese
civilization is three or three and a
half thousand years old and money for
itself its history is about three and a
half thousand years
uh so
um
right so uh
most likely older manipuri culture seems
to be actually older than Chinese
culture itself now the origins of the
people of Manipur is they're not quite
clear yet because of our historians our
scientists historians have not been
doing their job I mean what are the
great historians of the University of
imphal doing I'm not sure what they're
doing but they are not they are unable
to answer the question so what is the
origin of the manipuri language where
did it actually originate from we're not
quite sure that's fine
the question is uh so the manipuri
scriptures are called the puyas
uh and the puyas are very similar in
some ways to The Vedas uh the cosmology
is very interesting uh there is well you
know the cyclical theory of the universe
just like what we have in The Vedas uh I
was speaking to a manipuri friend
recently and he was saying that there
are apparently seven big Banks or seven
Cycles thus far according to the
manipuri puyas you know the methi puyas
that's interesting and it's obviously a
polytheistic system so you have uh
and so on so forth so that's in some
ways very similar to The Vedic Pantheon
of gods I think every polytheistic
system is in some way or the other very
similar
um so I'm not sure if you could actually
equate sridaba with Shiva and Sanam Mahi
with Karthik and paken by with Ganesh
but the similarities are unmistakable I
think
uh all polytheistic cultures are very
similar you typically have a belief in
the Divinity of everything uh it's
called uh it's called pan psychism or
Cosmo psychism that the entire universe
is conscious every object has some
Consciousness every object has some
Divinity in it plants trees animals
mountains humans we have or we all have
some aspect of divinity in us uh the
belief in reincarnation the worship of
spirits of ancestors of of the spirits
of forests and trees and obviously a
certain Pantheon of gods you see this in
Hinduism in The Vedic Vedic religion you
see it in Sanam it's called Sanam you
see it in the old Indo-European religion
you see it in what's called tengirism
you see it in Shinto you see it
everywhere
yeah so that's why it is it looks so
similar I'm not sure that the manipuri
is culture originated in in Vedic
culture most likely it did not most
likely it did not right
uh the kanglasha is the great uh the the
mythical Beast that guards the kangla
fort let's put that on the screen
so let's let's put that on the screen so
it seems to be a unicorn kind of
creature
it has uh no I'm not sure if it's a
unicorn take a look at this this is uh
the statue outside of the kangla fort
it has two horns and two branching horns
just like the antlers of a deer
yeah so that's a deal so that's what I
can say about this uh I'm not sure if
it's the same as the Chinese dragon lion
the what's the name of the Beast I
forget right
so yeah that's what it is
civilization older than the Chinese
civilization which means the manipuri
civilization is a more advanced Theology
of creation of the universe than the
Chinese culture yeah like I was just
saying the the the if you look at the
texts the puyas then there seems to be
that there is something very similar to
The Big Bang cosmology and what it's
something you find in The Vedic
cosmology as well the cyclical Rebirth
of the universe
so yes most likely manipuri civilization
methi civilization is most likely older
than the Chinese civilization and and
its Theology and theory of creation of
the universe is most likely more
sophisticated than the Chinese
Theory the Chinese culture yes indeed
okay let's take some more questions uh
son darang says can you tell us about
why there will be an earthquake in
Northeast India as I'm from arunachal
Pradesh a scientist has predicted
predicted that there will be an
earthquake in the Northeast the same
scientist who predicted an earthquake in
Turkey mild earthquakes happen in my
state here in there every two three
months and nobody cares it's a routine
thing yes
um hope we get not enough ideas and
knowledge to prevent people from dying
in the future look there is no
scientific
way of predicting Earth predicting
earthquakes as of today as far as I know
people do make claims of having
predicted something I mean I can make a
prediction that there's going to be a
big earthquake in the Himalayas and I
will refrain from giving a time frame so
it could happen in the next five years
next 10 years or next 50 years it's
gonna happen we know the Himalayas are
an extremely seismically active Zone a
big earthquake is inevitably going to
happen sometime in the future so let's
say I make the prediction there's gonna
be a big earthquake in the Himalayas
again
well that's no prediction unless you
give a proper time frame or a time scale
to it
so somebody if somebody predicts there's
going to be an earthquake in Turkey it's
not necessarily a scientific prediction
even though that person may be a
scientist because there is no way as of
today of accurately predicting
earthquakes
the Earth how does an earthquake occur
how does it happen what's the mechanism
it's underground tectonic activity the
movements of the tectonic plates under
the surface of the Earth
and these movements happen because of
the internal convection movement of the
magma layer within the Earth in deep in
the interior of the Earth
and sometimes the magma comes up to the
surface of the Earth in the form of
volcanoes that's lava and that's why the
the the ring of fire which a ring of
volcanoes and where you have lots of
earthquakes Indonesia Japan all that
right all the way up to the andamans
so because we don't know what's
happening deep under the Earth's surface
that's why we are not in a position to
make any accurate predictions of
earthquakes so I am sure the media must
have reported this or that that
so-and-so person made a prediction the
me the media people are not scientists
and they they look for sensationalism so
one must not be believe everything that
appears in the media it's actually 95 of
what appears in the media has to be
cross-checked very
thoroughly because it could be highly
inaccurate so
will there be earthquakes in the future
in the Northeast yes
you have both questions time to time
like like uh sundarang is saying every
two three months there's a small
earthquake here and there in in
arunachal Pradesh and there are
earthquakes throughout the Far East of
India the northeast of India Manipur
nagaland even Myanmar and obviously the
Andaman Islands so why do earthquakes
happen it's they happen because of
tectonic activity the Indian plate 100
million years ago the Indian
subcontinent was attached to Africa
about 120 million years ago then because
of tectonic activity It sped across the
Indian Ocean and slammed into Eurasia
and this action of in the Indian
subcontinent slamming into Eurasia
created the Himalayas and the Himalayas
are still Rising the Indian Place
subcontinent is still slamming into
Eurasia it's a slow-motion Collision but
an extremely energetic collision and
these enormous forces they push these
mountains upwards and that tells you
that the Himalayan region is highly
unstable
and that's why you have earthquakes
there every few
years or decades you have a major
earthquake in this area and the Far East
of India Northeast of India arunachal
Pradesh nagaland uh Manipur Etc that's
in the foothills of the Himalayas you
have Hills it's a very hilly place so
because it's part
of the extended Himalayan Zone that's
why you have earthquakes there so that's
why there are earthquakes on a fairly
routine basis
Etc and that's why in the future also
this will continue to happen for the
foreseeable future when you talk about
geological time scales you're talking
about tens of millions of years so it's
gonna be a feature of this region just
like in Japan you know earthquakes
happen it's just a way of life it's a
fact of life similarly in the northeast
of India it's going to happen but
hopefully not to that extent not very
major earthquakes
swapnil says what makes tardigrades the
toughest animal species on Earth
physically chemically biologically uh
that can withstand just about any
natural Calamity or extreme environment
interesting question what is a
tardigrade let's Google it
let us Google it so that I can show the
image of what it taught to get it start
the grid looks like
here is Google
tar B grade
that is a spelling it's an animal it's
about half a millimeter in size it's
also called a water bear colloquially
that's what it looks like let us go to
images that's what it looks like a
tardigrade that's what it is
so it kind of looks like a bear yes it
has this bear like face as well and bear
polar bear like like like body as well
they're called water bears colloquially
so these are microscopic creatures about
half a millimeter in in length a very
small and they are found all across the
Earth in virtually every habitat in the
earth they are found in the sea they're
tall they're found on the top of hills
and mountains there's found in deserts
they're found everywhere they found all
around us uh
why are they so hardy why are they so
tough so they have certain
uh
adaptations that give them the toughness
so these beasts these little beasts can
survive extreme pressure you go to the
deep sea trenches the Mariana trencher
the deep sea trenches where the ocean is
several kilometers deep which is going
to be a place where you have extremely
high pressure tardigrades can survive
that they can also survive extreme
temperatures the temperature on the Moon
the highest temperature during daytime
is about 130 degrees Celsius and the low
temperature on Moon is about minus 150
Celsius so tar degrees can tardigrades
can survive that temperature easily they
can survive temperatures below to minus
200 degrees
and that they can survive temperatures
above 151 degrees Celsius higher than
the boiling point of water they can
survive that easily yeah they can also
survive extreme dehydration uh they they
uh they go into a state of hibernation
they go into a state of extreme
dehydration
uh in which their motor metabolism comes
to a complete halt
and they can survive for decades in this
kind of dehydrated States so they are
not physically active their metabolism
is completely stopped but they survive
in this state of suspended animation
dehydration and in this condition they
can even survive exposure to the vacuum
of space so they can survive on the moon
they can survive on the exterior of
spacecrafts and all that and they are
even able to repair their DNA they have
this incredible ability to repair the
DNA if you send somebody to space even
if you are shielded and within a
spacecraft you're going to be exposed to
cosmic rays Cosmic radiation
which can damage and degrade your DNA
which can create mutations and Cancers
and all that well tardigrants are able
to repair the DNA somehow so this
protects them from the damage caused by
radiation in outer space so they have
certain proteins that protect their DNA
from the damage caused by radiation
X-rays and cosmic rays and all those
things and they also have a certain
protein which protects them which which
enables them to survive without oxygen
so they're able to survive in space they
are able to withstand radiation x-rays
cosmic rays they're able to withstand
extreme temperatures extreme pressures
they they can survive without oxygen and
they can uh you know they can survive in
extreme environments so it's because of
these they can even survive exposure to
toxic chemicals and acids and alkaline
environments they also have a very
tough exterior Pro coating
a thick shell so to say which helps them
survive these things so because of all
these adaptations genetic adaptations
evolutionary adaptations that's what
makes the tardigrade so incredibly tough
and Hardy it can survive just about
anything uh recently this there was an
Israeli spacecraft that crashed on the
moon it was carrying tardigrades for
research purposes so those tardigrades
are now on the moon surface and I assure
you they're alive
yeah so that's the kind of incredible
Beast little tiny little beast it is
just half a millimeter in length and
yeah it's possibly the toughest creature
on that we know of on planet Earth
they just says Canada solar system have
more undiscovered planets than what we
know currently if yes why are they not
discovered yet yes the solar system most
likely has undiscovered Planet there
already seems to be there's a big search
going on right now for planet nine
or Planet X or whatever you want to call
it so if you look at the orbits of
various uh
objects in the solar system there seems
to be a disturbance in the force so to
say uh beyond the orbit of Pluto so
there is most likely a hidden Planet
Somewhere Out There far away from the
orbit of Pluto Pluto further beyond the
orbit of Pluto uh but it's not
detectable thus far
astronomers all around the world are
looking for it
um
so it's it's existence is inferred from
from studying the orbits of various
other objects in the solar system
um and the solar system is very large
the solar system extends more than one
light year out away from the Sun Way
Beyond the orbit of Pluto and it could
be harboring all kinds of objects there
are so far away that the sunlight
doesn't quite reach them and even if it
reaches them it doesn't quite the
objects may be dark in color reddish
dark I mean lots of objects in the
trans-nept union objects Etc are Reddish
in color because of various chemicals
organic chemicals and hydrocarbons so if
an object is reddish or dark in color
then even if you shine a lot of light on
it it's not going to be easy to find and
especially when it is so far away that
the light that reaches it is very dim
sunlight so there are lots of reasons
why there could be many many
undiscovered planets and other objects
out there in the far reaches of the
solar system
it's most likely that we're going to
have lots of new discoveries in the
coming decades as our abilities to
search for such objects get better as we
have more powerful telescopes and other
techniques so the reason they aren't
discovered here is because they are so
far away that they are they'll be that
very little sunlight reaches them the
sunlight that reaches them is very faint
and they could be dark in color their
their surface would be dark which makes
it even harder for us to find it
yes
okay I have a lot lot more questions
that I obviously will not be able to
take today let's take one more
tanvi says when we talk about UFOs we
all always think of them as a disc
shaped structure how did we come up with
specifically that shape and why did the
world accept it as what it is the way
the way it is portrayed is there any
scientific reason for this
there is no scientific reason for a
spacecraft or UFO to have a disc
structure they look at
the various spacecraft we send into
orbit look at the various uh aircraft we
have
commercial planes fighter planes other
planes helicopters none of them look
like discs
uh look at the spacecraft we have in in
Earth's orbit satellites none of them
look like disks so why do we all think
of UFOs as disks or saucers it's because
of the early media
uh exposure or coverage of this in the
United States
so apparently some pilot observed an
object that looked like a flying saucer
looked like a saucer saucer shaped and
it was flying that's what he claimed and
that became a big media sensation
and then you had the Rose Bowl Roosevelt
incident in which the American Military
claims it was a weather balloon that
crashed and eyewitnesses said that it
was shaped like a saucer or something so
because of this initial media frenzy
about the saucer shape that's why it's
always become ingrained in the public
imagination that UFOs are gonna be
shaped like saucers and then people
imagine that lots lots of it is
obviously imagined lots of it is just
false claims
and obviously you also have weather
balloons these are the spherical objects
that typically go very high up in the
atmosphere maybe 40 50 60 000 kilometers
or 60 000 meters not kilometers meters
above the surface so 40 50 60 kilometers
above the surface you know
in the stratosphere and all that so if
you look at such an object from the
ground it's gonna look not spherical but
disc shaped so that also could have
contributed to the sightings the
reported sightings of
disc shaped UFOs
so it's something that's become part of
the popular imagination the media always
portrays it like that various science
fiction series and cartoons and all that
they portray it like that uh whether it
is V from the 1980s which was a remade
in the late 2000s
whether it is anything else even even
the Star Trek
um what is it called the USS Enterprises
kind of disc shaped so it's become part
of the public imagination and
Consciousness but there is no scientific
reason for it or need for a UFO or any
spacecraft or flying object to have a
disc shape
foreign
all right let's take some live chat
questions now I have a bunch of other
questions which I'm not gonna be able to
take
but let's take some let's take one more
saurabh says who am I mind or Beyond
mind this is a philosophical question
who am I
am I the Mind am I something beyond the
Mind am I this body so we all identify
very strongly with the body that we we
inhabit
but what we truly are is the mind the
Consciousness right and we we know very
well that the seat or root of the
Consciousness is the brain
right we don't we identify more with our
face and our head in our eyes in this
region than any other part of the body
and our Consciousness obviously is
connected to the brain I mean if
somebody has a traumatic brain injury
the Consciousness is lost and the person
dies
but
philosophically
so there are lots of philosophical
schools of thought that give you
different answers to this uh
scientifically we don't know because
science is limited to physical objects
and physical phenomena
empirical evidence but
um clearly there is something
called Consciousness that all living
beings share the human consciousness
seems to be the highest Consciousness
but even dogs cats cows Turtles fish
insects seem to have some level of
consciousness
well even even microorganisms are aware
of their environment and they take steps
to protect themselves when a threat
appears so there seems to be some level
of awareness with maybe very rudimentary
awareness there
and there's obviously the the the
philosophical view especially in
Hinduism that uh there is a universal
Consciousness and we are local
manifestations of that
it's kind of like Quantum field Theory
where there's a Quantum field of and and
particles are are local excitations on
that field so it kind of is similar to
that
uh so we don't have the answers
obviously a philosophy tells you certain
things it gives you certain answers but
there is no scientific evidence for that
so obviously you cannot mix science and
philosophy certain things are Beyond
science
science cannot answer certain questions
right now because it is limited because
over our our apparatuses are limited our
our uh understanding is limited our
intelligence is limited so obviously
there's a whole lot out there that
science cannot explain and maybe science
is not supposed to delve into those
matters science only deals with the
physically physical
Universe physical objects and physical
phenomena
Consciousness we're not sure if it's a
physical phenomenon
the mind and the Soul These Are
Spiritual objects non-physical objects
they are beyond the realm of science so
who am I am I mind am I beyond mind I
don't know uh from a scientific
perspective uh I can't say much about
that from a philosophical perspective
from the dharmic viewpoint
uh mind is
well the soul is eternal
and there is a universal Consciousness
that we are all part of and we are all
connected to and everything is conscious
to some extent including non-living
objects as well that's what Indian or
Hindu philosophy tells you so that's two
different perspectives I can offer right
let's take some live chat questions
live chat questions
you are Indian hahaha so what do I seem
to be do I seem to be something else I'm
not sure if the
okay okay if you have any questions
please let me know please ask me in the
live chat right now I'll take them for
about five or ten minutes from the live
chat
uh
Nishan says is there any connection
between The Vedic God indra's killing of
ritra and the Sumerian Gilgamesh flood
story there could be or maybe maybe not
see the Sumerian story is is diff
Sumerian culture so Millions mythology
may have some connections with ancient
Vedic uh
cultural mythology but it's not really
well demonstrated uh and the killing of
varithra did not unleash a flood it
seemedly it simply
freed the Waters of the world
now the story is that vitra was this
Great Serpent the great he he is the
ancient Sanskrit word for snake serpent
Ahi and it can also be translated as
well perhaps as Dragon so the great
ahibitra had encircled the ocean and all
the Waters of the world and there was a
big drought as a consequence so Indra
had to go and defeat this Great Serpent
and he defeated The Serpent and the
waters were released and the world was
well again but yeah it kind of
uh raises the possibility that initially
there could have been a flood and I
think that does seem to be a flood story
in ancient Indian mythology as well
which could be a memory of a very
ancient flood so it is a possibility but
we are not able to find a one-to-one
correspondence between the the flood
epics of of Sumeria and Mesopotamia and
the biblical flood epic and uh flood
myths and other flood myths that seem to
be a worldwide phenomenon but there
could be a possible connection we don't
know for sure we did more research
okay
what other questions do we have
um
what are those Indian yashika says what
are those Indian Idols found out found
in Colombia
is Indian culture related to Native
Americans by any chance I'm not sure if
I've seen any Indian Idols found in
Colombia obviously in Colombia in South
America in Central America as well in
North America as well you had a
polytheistic uh culture which was
destroyed by the Europeans and you had
it was polytheistic and you had idols
and representations of various gods and
goddesses and divinities
which is the plumed serpent and
many others yeah so many of these
polytheistic representations of of gods
and goddesses and divinities would look
like certain Indian gods so there seems
to be some kind of
what you would call circumstantial
similarity between the two but uh is
there any proof genuine hard evidence
that there is a correspondence or
connection we don't know so I would not
agree that I would not go so far as to
call those Idols Indian Idols thus far
from whatever knowledge and evidence we
have as of today in the future evidence
May emerge that there was
contact between ancient India and the
ancient Americas there seems to be some
some
genetic
research coming out that could possibly
point in the direction pomegranate
uh genetics and all that but as of today
we don't quite have enough information
to make such a claim as of today
right
[Music]
um
somnath Abhishek says increase of
Espionage within defense are we going to
see something big in the region
Espionage is always a big part of
Defense what evidence do we have that
there is an increase in Espionage where
in India and Pakistan in Afghanistan and
Sri Lanka in China where exactly
Espionage is never something that's
visible
even if there's a lot of
Espionage activity going on right now
it's not going to be visible to you and
me we're not supposed to see it
so yeah I don't know anything
I I am I know only what you all what
everybody else knows I don't have any
access to special privileged information
that only some people have I'm not I
don't have any of that so yeah I'm not
aware of any increase of espionage
and therefore I don't know
uh other questions
I just answered this question
uh Shaheen says how
um we saw how cost efficient it is to
spy on your foe by using balloons my
question is whether our government is
doing something similar if not how can
we develop the strategy I don't think
India is doing any such thing as far as
I know
it is indeed cost efficient to spy on
your foes using balloons balloons are
very hard to detect especially if
they're flying very high so your radar
systems may not detect them radar
systems are designed to detect hard
objects
fighter planes and other aerial assets
balloons are soft
objects that are not metallic mostly
almost no metal at all so it's they
would easily evade detection by radar
and thus thus they would not trigger any
uh alarms
so yeah it's it's a good tactic or
strategy to use it it's gonna be useful
in some ways it can loiter over an area
and you know give you a lot of detailed
imagery of the area
I don't think India is doing that
how can we develop it well build
construct balloons it's not a very
high-tech methodology
uh the equipment you can place as a
payload on a balloon can be high-tech
but I don't think it's it takes a great
deal of technological expertise to to
make to to construct a high altitude
balloon
I'm sure you can develop the technology
within six months or a year if you don't
have it but considering the kind of
scientific and Engineering expertise
India has why is India not doing this
well I don't know
I don't know
right okay what else some other
questions
can we really trust Israel as it is in
American satellite state we can trust
Israel to prioritize its National
interest the same way we can trust China
to prioritize its National interest and
so on so wherever our national interest
converges with Israel's National
interest we can trust them
so obviously we should be able to
predict what their perception of their
interests is going to be like and we
also have to be cognizant of the fact
that there is a significant American
influence in Israel so we should know
what the parameters of our cooperation
should be what lines we should not cross
and where we should refrain from
trusting too much all those things we
should know
so yeah that's the answer
um
okay what else do we have other
questions I think there are lots of
questions many of them have answered
before do I follow F1 racing no I don't
follow from fundraising I haven't
followed it for at least two decades as
a kid I found it somewhat interesting I
remember uh these uh
there used to be these guys there was a
guy called Allah post french guy
Ayrton Senna who tragically died in 1997
I think Imola I believe it was
uh the great uh Michael Schumacher
obviously
Nikki Lauda and and many other greats so
as a kid I was kind of interested in it
but afterwards I kind of uh lost touch
and lost interest so I don't follow it
anymore
uh what else do we have
um
MCU what's MCU Marvel Cinematic Universe
is it I saw a couple of original I mean
movies initially
I think I saw one or two Iron Man movies
I saw
Guardians of the Galaxy or something
I am Groot or whatever group yeah that
the three three fellow
and uh Dave Batista is that alien with
no expression and all that I saw a
couple of these movies
recently I saw that Multiverse of misery
Madness something
and I saw a movie recently with that red
woman Red Witch or something I've seen a
few random movies here and there I don't
find them interesting at all there's no
story it's just rehashing the same old
thing 75 different characters how can
you follow any character Arc if there
are so many characters
so initially the Iron Man was
interesting the first one was good at
least you know uh
Spider-Man I've seen the original 203
Spider-Man movies they oh the previous
the the
2000s Spider-Man and so on yeah I've
seen a few of those yeah
I've kind of lost interest it's not
interesting I'm a huge fan of movies you
know I love I love watching movies uh if
I had my way I would watch two movies
every week or in on the big screen in a
cinema if you if the cinemas would show
good movies yeah but yeah uh these days
there's something nice and they're not
making anything interesting
okay do we have any other questions we
have obviously but uh
what are exoplanets and how do
scientists search for life on other
planets exoplanets are planets in orbit
around other stars not the Sun so the we
have thus far found I think thousands of
exoplanets planets in orbit around other
stars far away from here from our solar
system so yes that's what an exoplanet
is there are different kinds of
exoplanets there are there are the gas
giants there are the hot Jupiters that
are Jupiter sized uh gas giants in a
very tight orbit around around their
star like orbit that takes 24 hours or
less you know or maybe a week even
that's again even that's a hot Jupiter
so that's a planet that's losing its
atmosphere it's boiling off when you
have rocky terrestrial planets the newer
planets in the in the in the Goldilocks
zone where liquid water can flow and so
on so that's what exoplanets are how do
scientists search for life on other
parents so they do it through
spectroscopy to try and see the
spectroscopic um
makeup of the gases in the atmosphere of
a planet from that you can infer the
existence of water wafer Vapor maybe
nitrogen maybe ammonia maybe certain
other
uh gases that could be
could be indicators of the of the
existence of Life on those planets so
thus far we do it through spectroscopic
means the games web Space Telescope is
is a good tool for doing this so that's
how scientists are searching for life on
other plants right now right now we
don't quite have the means to do more
detailed studies
okay my dear friends we are well past
two hours so I think I'm gonna end this
session right here as always I had many
more questions I had selected and I was
not able to answer them all but we're
gonna continue the story we're gonna
continue the episodes and I'm I'm gonna
answer as many
questions of yours as I can every week
so this brings us to the end of today's
episode thank you very much for watching
and I will see you very soon next week
until then take care and see you soon
bye